<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Copyright 2006-2015 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<section id="actions-wait">
    <title>Wait</title>

    <para>This action shows how to make the test framework wait until a certain condition is satisfied. The attribute
      'time' defines the amount of time to wait in seconds. The attribute 'testInterval' defines the amount of time to
      wait *between* each check. If the check does not exceed within the defined 'time' then the test execution fails
      with an appropriate error message. Different conditions can be checked, depending on your use-case. If you
      want to check if a web-server is running then use the 'http' condition. Or if you would like to check for the
      presence of a file then use the file check. Examples of both are shown below.
    </para>
    
    <para><emphasis>XML DSL</emphasis></para>
    <programlisting>&lt;testcase name=&quot;waitTest&quot;&gt;
    &lt;actions&gt;
        &lt;wait time=&quot;10&quot; testInterval=&quot;2&quot; &gt;

        &lt;http url=&quot;http://a.b.c/&quot; statusCode=&quot;200&quot; timeout=&quot;2&quot; /&gt;

        &lt;wait/&gt;
    &lt;/actions&gt;
&lt;/testcase&gt;</programlisting>

    <para><emphasis>Java DSL designer and runner</emphasis></para>
    <programlisting language="java">@CitrusTest
public void waitTest() {
    wait(10); // wait in total for 10 seconds, repeating the check every 2 seconds
}</programlisting>
    
    <para>When should somebody use this action? This action is very useful when you want your test to wait for a certain
      event to occur before continuing with the test execution. For example if you wish that your test waits until a docker
      container is started or for an application to create a log file before continuing, then use this action. You can
      also create your own Conditions ... TODO CD is this possible when using the XML DSL?
    </para>
</section>