<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="changes-new">
  <title>What's new in Citrus 2.5?!</title>

  <para>We have added lots of new features and improvements with Citrus 2.5. Namely these are new modules for RMI and JMX support, a new x-www-form-urlencoded message validator. Just have a look at the following overview on what has changed.</para>

  <section id="new-2-5-rmi">
    <title>RMI support</title>

    <para>Remote method invocation is a standard Java technology and API for calling methods on remote objects across different JVM instances. Although RMI has lost its popularity it is still used in legacy components. Testing
    RMI bean invocation is a hard thing to do. Now Citrus provides client and server support for remote interface invocation. See <xref linkend="rmi"/> for details.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="new-2-5-jmx">
    <title>JMX support</title>

    <para>Similar to RMI JMX can be used to connect to remote bean invocation. This time we expose some beans to a managed bean server in order to be managed by JMX operations for read and write.
    With Citrus 2.5 we have added a client and server support for calling and providing managed beans on a mbean server. See <xref linkend="jmx"/> for details.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="new-2-5-form-urlencoded">
    <title>Http x-www-form-urlencoded message validator</title>

    <para>HTML form data can be transmitted with different methods and content types. One of the most common ways is to use <emphasis>x-www-form-urlencoded</emphasis> form data
    content. As validation can be tricky we have added a special message validator for that. See <xref linkend="http-www-form-urlencoded"/> for details.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="new-2-5-bugfixes">
    <title>Bugfixes</title>

    <para>Bugs are part of our software developers world and fixing them is part of your daily business, too. Finding and solving issues
      makes Citrus better every day. For a detailed listing of all bugfixes please refer to the complete changes log of each release in
      JIRA (<ulink url="http://www.citrusframework.org/changes-report.html">http://www.citrusframework.org/changes-report.html</ulink>).</para>
  </section>

</chapter>