<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="changes-new">
  <title>What's new in Citrus 2.6?!</title>

  <para>Citrus 2.6 comes with a set of new modules that enable completely new aspects of integration testing. Namely these are the new modules for Cucumber behavior driven development and Zookeeper support.
  Just have a look at the following features that are shipped within the 2.6 box.</para>

  <section id="new-2-6-cucumber">
    <title>Cucumber BDD support</title>

    <para>Behavior driven development is more and more coming up also in the integration testing environment. Cucumber is a fantastic behavior driven development library that provides support for BDD concepts with Gherkin. The
      new Citrus integration with Cucumber enables the mix of Gherkin syntax feature scenarios with Citrus test case execution. You write feature stories as usual and create Citrus test cases with lots of actions for the integration
      test. See details for this feature in <xref linkend="cucumber"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="new-2-6-zookeeper">
    <title>Zookeeper support</title>

    <para>Zookeeper from Apache lets you manage configuration with distributed coordination. As a user you create and edit values on a Zookeeper server. Other clients then can retrieve this information. With Citrus you are able to
      access this information from within a test case. The Zookeeper Citrus client lets you manage information on the Zookeeper server. See details for this feature in <xref linkend="zookeeper"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="new-2-6-restdocs">
    <title>Spring Restdocs support</title>

    <para>Restdocs is a fantastic way of generating documentation for RESTful APIs. While exchanging request/response data with the server Restdocs creates documentation information on the data. The documentation includes field descriptions,
      headers and snippets for body content. With new Citrus version Http clients in Citrus can add Restdoc interceptors that generate the documentation while executing the test cases. This way you are able to document what messages were exchanged
      in tests. The Restdocs support is also available for the SOAP Http client in Citrus. See details in <xref linkend="restdocs"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="new-2-6-hamcrest-conditions">
    <title>Hamcrest matcher conditions</title>

    <para>Iterating test action containers in Citrus evaluate boolean expressions for determination of how to execute the nested actions in a loop. Also the conditional container executes nested actions based on boolean expression evaluation.
      The Citrus boolean expression support is limited to very basic operations such as lower than or greater than. Furthermore the combination of boolean expressions with variables has not been supported. Following from that we have improved the
      boolean expression evaluation mechanism with extension to Hamcrest matchers. So now you can evaluate matchers in iterating conditions. This feature is described in <xref linkend="containers-conditional"/> and <xref linkend="containers-iterate"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="new-2-6-soap-dsl">
    <title>SOAP Java DSL</title>

    <para>Citrus provides a new Java fluent API for sending and receiving SOAP related message content. The Java DSL enhancements are
    based on those of Http. Now you can define SOAP messages with special SOAP action headers more easily. On top of that you can handle SOAP faults
    on client and server with the fluent API. Checkout <xref linkend="soap-webservices"/> for details.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="new-2-6-refactoring">
    <title>Refactoring</title>

    <para>Refactoring in terms of simplification and standardization is part of our daily life as a developer. We have been working
    on improving the Java DSL fluent API for SOAP. We also introduced a more common way of handling the test action containers like iterate,
    parallel and so on. This leads to some classes and methods that were marked as deprecated. So please have a look at your Java DSL code and if
    you see some usage of deprecated stuff please use the new approaches as soon as possible. The deprecated stuff will definitely disappear in upcoming
    releases.</para>

    <para>Some of the changes that we have made might hit you right away. These changes are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>ws:assert</emphasis> element in SOAP testcase schema has been renamed to <emphasis>ws:assert-fault</emphasis>. This was done for
          better interoperability reasons with <emphasis>assert</emphasis> action in core schema and to be compliant to <emphasis>send-fault</emphasis> action.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Java DSL module has had Maven dependencies to several other modules in Citrus (e.g. citrus-jms, citrus-soap). These dependencies were
          declared as compile dependencies, which is not very nice as you might not need JMS or SOAP functionalities in your project. We have added
          optional and provided markers to that dependencies which means that you have to decide in your project which of the modules to include.
        </para>

        <para>You may face some missing dependencies errors when running the Maven project. As a result you need to include the Citrus modules
        (e.g. citrus-http, citrus-docker, and so on) in your project Maven POM explicitly.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="new-2-6-bugfixes">
    <title>Bugfixes</title>

    <para>Bugs are part of our software developers world and fixing them is part of your daily business, too. Finding and solving issues
      makes Citrus better every day. For a detailed listing of all bugfixes please refer to the complete changes log of each release in
      JIRA (<ulink url="http://www.citrusframework.org/changes-report.html">http://www.citrusframework.org/changes-report.html</ulink>).</para>
  </section>

</chapter>