<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="http">
    <title>Http support</title>

    <para>Citrus is able to connect with Http services and simulate RESTful WebServices servers. In the next sections you will learn
    how to invoke Http services and how to handle REST Http requests in a test case. We deal with setting up a Http server in order to
    accept client requests and provide proper Http responses with GET, PUT, DELETE or POST request method.</para>
    
    <note>
        <para>Similar to the JMS specific configuration schema, Citrus provides a customized Http configuration schema that
        is used in Spring configuration files. Simply include the http-config namespace in the configuration XML files as follows.</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;beans xmlns=&quot;http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans&quot;
   xmlns:xsi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance&quot;
   xmlns:citrus=&quot;http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/config&quot;
   xmlns:citrus-http=&quot;http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/http/config&quot;
   xsi:schemaLocation=&quot;
   http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans 
   http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans.xsd
   http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/config 
   http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/config/citrus-config.xsd
   http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/http/config 
   http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/http/config/citrus-http-config.xsd&quot;&gt;
       
    [...]
    
&lt;/beans&gt;</programlisting>
        
        <para>Now you are ready to use the customized Http configuration elements with the 
        citrus-http namespace prefix.</para>
    </note>
    
    <section id="http-sender">
        <title>Http message sender</title>
        
        <para>Citrus is able to invoke a Http service as client waiting for the response message from server. After that the response message goes 
        through the validation process as usual. Let us see how a message sender for Http works:</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;citrus-http:message-sender id=&quot;httpMessageSender&quot; 
                               request-url=&quot;http://localhost:8090/test&quot; 
                               request-method=&quot;POST&quot;
                               content-type=&quot;application/xml&quot;
                               reply-handler=&quot;httpResponseHandler&quot;/&gt;

&lt;citrus-http:reply-message-handler id=&quot;httpResponseHandler&quot;/&gt;</programlisting>
        
        <para>As Http communication is always synchronous we need a reply message handler in combination with the Http message-sender. It is not
        very surprising that the sender also needs the <emphasis>request-url</emphasis> and a <emphasis>request-method</emphasis> as parameter. In addition
        to that we can specify the content-type of the request we are about to send. The message sender builds the Http request and sends it to the Http server. 
        The Http response is then provided to the reply handler as soon as it has arrived.</para>
        
        <para>The request method is statically set to <emphasis>POST</emphasis> in the example above. You can also set/overwrite the Http request method inside the 
        sending test action which gives more flexibility. Use something like this in your test:</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;send with=&quot;httpMessageSender&quot;&gt;
      &lt;message&gt;
          &lt;data&gt;
              &lt;![CDATA[
                  &lt;testRequestMessage&gt;
                      &lt;text&gt;Hello HttpServer&lt;/text&gt;
                  &lt;/testRequestMessage&gt;
              ]]&gt;
          &lt;/data&gt;
      &lt;/message&gt;
      &lt;header&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;citrus_http_method&quot; value=&quot;PUT&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;/header&gt;
  &lt;/send&gt;</programlisting>
        
        <tip><para>Citrus uses Spring's REST template mechanism for sedning Http requests. This means you have great customizing opportunities with a special REST 
        template configuration. You can think of basic Http authentication, read timeouts and special message factory implementations. Just use the custom REST template
        attribute in message sender like this:</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;citrus-http:message-sender id=&quot;httpMessageSender&quot; 
                               request-url=&quot;http://localhost:8090/test&quot; 
                               request-method=&quot;POST&quot;
                               content-type=&quot;text/plain&quot;
                               rest-template=&quot;customizedRestTemplate&quot;
                               reply-handler=&quot;httpResponseHandler&quot;/&gt;
                               
  &lt;!-- Customized rest template --&gt;
  &lt;bean name=&quot;customizedRestTemplate&quot; class=&quot;org.springframework.web.client.RestTemplate&quot;&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;messageConverters&quot;&gt;
      &lt;util:list id=&quot;converter&quot;&gt;
        &lt;bean class=&quot;org.springframework.http.converter.StringHttpMessageConverter&quot;&gt;
          &lt;property name=&quot;supportedMediaTypes&quot;&gt;
            &lt;util:list id=&quot;types&quot;&gt;
              &lt;value&gt;text/plain&lt;/value&gt;
            &lt;/util:list&gt;
          &lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;/bean&gt;
      &lt;/util:list&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;errorHandler&quot;&gt;
      &lt;!-- Custom error handler --&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;requestFactory&quot;&gt;
      &lt;bean class=&quot;org.springframework.http.client.CommonsClientHttpRequestFactory&quot;&gt;
        &lt;property name=&quot;readTimeout&quot; value=&quot;9000&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;/bean&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
        </programlisting>
        </tip>
    </section>
    
    <section id="http-server">
        <title>Http server</title>
        
        <para>Sending Http messages was quite easy and straight forward. Receiving Http messages is a little bit more complicated, because Citrus 
        has to provide server functionality listening on a local port for client connections. Once a client connection 
        is accepted the Http server must also provide a proper Http response to the client. Citrus ships with an embedded Http server, which is a preconfigured Jetty  
        server instance with Spring web application context support.</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;citrus-http:server id=&quot;sinpleHttpServer&quot; 
                port=&quot;8090&quot;
                auto-start=&quot;true&quot;
                context-config-location=&quot;classpath:com/consol/citrus/http/citrus-servlet-context.xml&quot;
                resource-base=&quot;src/citrus/resources&quot;/&gt;
        </programlisting>
        
        <para>The Http Jetty server will automatically start when the Spring application context is loaded (auto-start=&quot;true&quot;). The basic connector is listening on
        port 8090 for requests. The server automatically uses Spring application context loading on startup. The servlet context file is specified via classpath and hold all custom
        configurations for the server. Here is a sample servlet context with some basic Spring MVC components and the central HttpMessageController which is responsible for handling
        incoming requests (GET, PUT, DELETE, POST, etc.).</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;bean class=&quot;org.springframework.web.servlet.mvc.annotation.DefaultAnnotationHandlerMapping&quot;/&gt;
  
  &lt;bean class=&quot;org.springframework.web.servlet.mvc.annotation.AnnotationMethodHandlerAdapter&quot;&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;messageConverters&quot;&gt;
      &lt;util:list id=&quot;converters&quot;&gt;
        &lt;bean class=&quot;org.springframework.http.converter.StringHttpMessageConverter&quot;&gt;
          &lt;property name=&quot;supportedMediaTypes&quot;&gt;
            &lt;util:list&gt;
              &lt;value&gt;text/xml&lt;/value&gt;
            &lt;/util:list&gt;
          &lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;/bean&gt;
      &lt;/util:list&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
        
  &lt;bean class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.http.controller.HttpMessageController&quot;&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;messageHandler&quot;&gt;
        &lt;bean id=&quot;emptyResponseProducingMessageHandler&quot; 
         class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.http.handler.EmptyResponseProducingMessageHandler&quot;/&gt;        
    &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
        </programlisting>
        
        <para>The beans above are responsible for proper Http server configuration. In general you do not need to adjust those beans, but we have the possibility to do so which gives 
        us a great customization and extension points. The important part is the message handler definition inside the HttpMessageController. Once a client request was accepted the 
        message handler is responsible for generating a proper response to the client.</para>
        
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata align="center" display="block" fileref="figure_009.jpg" format="JPG" />
          </imageobject>
          
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata align="center" display="block" fileref="figure_009.jpg" format="JPG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        
        <para>Citrus provides several message handler implementations for different simulation strategies. With these message handler implementations you should be able to generate
        proper response messages for the client in a test case. Let's have a look at them in the following sections.</para>
        
        <section id="http-message-handler-empty">
            <title>Empty response producing message handler</title>
            
            <para>This is the simplest message handler you can think of. It simply provides an empty success response using the Http
            response code 202. In the introducing example this message handler was used to provide response messages to the calling client.
            The handler does not need any configurations or properties as it simply responds with an empty Http response.</para>
            
            <programlisting>&lt;bean id=&quot;emptyResponseProducingMessageHandler&quot; 
  class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.http.handler.EmptyResponseProducingMessageHandler&quot;/&gt;</programlisting>
        </section>
        
        <section id="http-message-handler-static">
            <title>Static response producing message handler</title>
            
            <para>The next more complex message handler will always return a static response message</para>
            
            <programlisting>&lt;bean 
  class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.adapter.handler.StaticResponseProducingMessageHandler&quot;&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;messagePayload&quot;&gt;
        &lt;value&gt;
        &lt;![CDATA[
            &lt;ns0:Response 
                xmlns:ns0=&quot;http://www.consol.de/schemas/samples/sample.xsd&quot;&gt;
                &lt;ns0:MessageId&gt;123456789&lt;/ns0:MessageId&gt;
                &lt;ns0:CorrelationId&gt;CORR123456789&lt;/ns0:CorrelationId&gt;
                &lt;ns0:Text&gt;Hello User&lt;/ns0:Text&gt;
            &lt;/ns0:Response&gt;
        ]]&gt;
        &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;messageHeader&quot;&gt;
      &lt;map&gt;
        &lt;entry key=&quot;{http://www.consol.de/schemas/samples}ns0:Operation&quot; 
                  value=&quot;sayHelloResponse&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;entry key=&quot;{http://www.consol.de/schemas/samples}ns0:Request&quot; 
                  value=&quot;HelloRequest&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;/map&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>
            
            <para>The handler is configured with a static message payload and static response header values. The response to the client
            is therefore always identical.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section id="http-message-handler-xpath">
            <title>Xpath dispatching message handler</title>
            
            <para>The idea behind the xpath-dispatching-message-handler is that the incoming requests are dispatched to several
            message handlers according to an element value inside the message payload. The XPath expression will evaluate and
            call the respective message handler. The message handler mapping is done by their names inside a message handler Spring
            configuration context. The separate context is loaded in advance.</para>
            
            <programlisting>&lt;bean id=&quot;xpathDispatchingHandler&quot; 
  class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.http.handler.XpathDispatchingMessageHandler&quot;&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;xpathMappingExpression&quot; value=&quot;//MessageBody/Operation&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;messageHandlerContext&quot; value=&quot;message-handler-context.xml&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>
            
            <para>The handler receives a XPath mapping expression as well as a Spring ApllicationContext file resource. The message handlers
            are mapped to the different values via their names. For instance a incoming request with 
            <literal>//MessageBody/Operation = "getOrders"</literal> is handled by the message handler named "getOrders". The available message handlers
            are configured in the message-handler-context (e.g. EmptyResponseProducingMessageHandler, StaticResponseProducingMessageHandler, ...).</para>
        </section>
        
        <section id="http-message-handler-jms">
            <title>JMS connecting message handler</title>
            
            <para>The most powerful message handler is the JMS connecting message handler. Indeed this handler also provides the most 
            flexibility. This handler will forward incoming request to a JMS destination and waiting for a proper response on a reply destination. 
            A configured JMS message receiver can read this forwarded request internally over JMS and provide a proper response on the 
            reply destination.</para>
            
            <programlisting>&lt;bean id=&quot;jmsForwardingMessageHandler&quot; 
         class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.http.handler.JmsConnectingMessageHandler&quot;&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;destinationName&quot; value=&quot;JMS.Queue.Requests.In&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;replyDestinationName&quot; value=&quot;JMS.Queue.Response.Out&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;connectionFactory&quot;&gt;
        &lt;bean class=&quot;org.apache.activemq.ActiveMQConnectionFactory&quot;&gt;
            &lt;property name=&quot;brokerURL&quot; value=&quot;tcp://localhost:61616&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/bean&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name=&quot;replyTimeout&quot; value=&quot;2000&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>
            
            <tip>
                <para>The samples section may help you get in touch with the http configuration and the JMS forwarding stategy 
                (<xref linkend="samples"/>)</para>
            </tip>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section id="http-headers">
        <title>Http headers</title>
        
        <para>When dealing with Http request/response communication we always deal with Http specific headers. The Http protocol defines a goup of header attributes that both client 
        and server need to handle. You can set and validate these Http headers in Citrus quite easy. Let us have a look at a client operation in Citrus where some Http headers are 
        explicitly set before the request is sent.</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;send with=&quot;httpMessageSender&quot;&gt;
      &lt;message&gt;
          &lt;data&gt;
              &lt;![CDATA[
                  &lt;testRequestMessage&gt;
                      &lt;text&gt;Hello HttpServer&lt;/text&gt;
                  &lt;/testRequestMessage&gt;
              ]]&gt;
          &lt;/data&gt;
      &lt;/message&gt;
      &lt;header&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;CustomHeaderId&quot; value=&quot;${custom_header_id}&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;Content-Type&quot; value=&quot;text/xml&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;Accept&quot; value=&quot;text/xml,*/*&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;/header&gt;
  &lt;/send&gt;</programlisting>
        
        <para>We are able to set custom headers (<emphasis>CustomHeaderId</emphasis>) that go directly into the Http header section of the request. In addition to that testers can explicitly set Http reserved headers
        such as <emphasis>Content-Type</emphasis>. Fortunately you do not have to set all headers on your own. Citrus will automatically set the required Http headers for the request. So we have the following Http request
        which is sent to the server:</para>
        
        <programlisting>POST /test HTTP/1.1
Accept: text/xml, */*
Content-Type: text/xml
CustomHeaderId: 123456789
Accept-Charset: big5, big5-hkscs, euc-jp, euc-kr, gb18030, gb2312, gbk, ibm-thai, ibm00858, ibm01140, ibm01141, ibm01142, ibm01143, ibm01144, ibm01145, ibm01146, ibm01147, ibm01148, ibm01149, ibm037, ibm1026, ibm1047, ibm273, ibm277, ibm278, ibm280, ibm284, ibm285, ibm297, ibm420, ibm424, ibm437, ibm500, ibm775, ibm850, ibm852, ibm855, ibm857, ibm860, ibm861, ibm862, ibm863, ibm864, ibm865, ibm866, ibm868, ibm869, ibm870, ibm871, ibm918, iso-2022-cn, iso-2022-jp, iso-2022-jp-2, iso-2022-kr, iso-8859-1, iso-8859-13, iso-8859-15, iso-8859-2, iso-8859-3, iso-8859-4, iso-8859-5, iso-8859-6, iso-8859-7, iso-8859-8, iso-8859-9, jis_x0201, jis_x0212-1990, koi8-r, koi8-u, macroman, shift_jis, tis-620, us-ascii, utf-16, utf-16be, utf-16le, utf-32, utf-32be, utf-32le, utf-8, windows-1250, windows-1251, windows-1252, windows-1253, windows-1254, windows-1255, windows-1256, windows-1257, windows-1258, windows-31j, x-big5-solaris, x-euc-jp-linux, x-euc-tw, x-eucjp-open, x-ibm1006, x-ibm1025, x-ibm1046, x-ibm1097, x-ibm1098, x-ibm1112, x-ibm1122, x-ibm1123, x-ibm1124, x-ibm1381, x-ibm1383, x-ibm33722, x-ibm737, x-ibm833, x-ibm834, x-ibm856, x-ibm874, x-ibm875, x-ibm921, x-ibm922, x-ibm930, x-ibm933, x-ibm935, x-ibm937, x-ibm939, x-ibm942, x-ibm942c, x-ibm943, x-ibm943c, x-ibm948, x-ibm949, x-ibm949c, x-ibm950, x-ibm964, x-ibm970, x-iscii91, x-iso-2022-cn-cns, x-iso-2022-cn-gb, x-iso-8859-11, x-jis0208, x-jisautodetect, x-johab, x-macarabic, x-maccentraleurope, x-maccroatian, x-maccyrillic, x-macdingbat, x-macgreek, x-machebrew, x-maciceland, x-macromania, x-macsymbol, x-macthai, x-macturkish, x-macukraine, x-ms932_0213, x-ms950-hkscs, x-mswin-936, x-pck, x-sjis_0213, x-utf-16le-bom, x-utf-32be-bom, x-utf-32le-bom, x-windows-50220, x-windows-50221, x-windows-874, x-windows-949, x-windows-950, x-windows-iso2022jp
User-Agent: Jakarta Commons-HttpClient/3.1
Host: localhost:8091
Content-Length: 175
  &lt;testRequestMessage&gt;
      &lt;text&gt;Hello HttpServer&lt;/text&gt;
  &lt;/testRequestMessage&gt;</programlisting>
        
        <para>On server side testers are interested in validating the Http headers. Within Citrus receive action you simply define the expected header entries. The Http specific headers are automatically available for validation
        as you can see in this example:</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;receive with=&quot;httpRequestReceiver&quot;&gt;
      &lt;message&gt;
          &lt;data&gt;
              &lt;![CDATA[
                  &lt;testRequestMessage&gt;
                      &lt;text&gt;Hello HttpServer&lt;/text&gt;
                  &lt;/testRequestMessage&gt;
              ]]&gt;
          &lt;/data&gt;
      &lt;/message&gt;
      &lt;header&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;CustomHeaderId&quot; value=&quot;${custom_header_id}&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;Content-Type&quot; value=&quot;text/xml&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;Accept&quot; value=&quot;text/xml,*/*&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;/header&gt;
  &lt;/receive&gt;</programlisting>
        
        <para>The test checks on custom headers and Http specific headers to meet the expected values.</para>
        
        <para>Now that we have accepted the client request and validated the contents we are able to send back a proper Http response message. Same thing here with Http specific headers. The Http protcol defines several headers marking the success or failure of
        the server operation. In the test case you can set those headers for the response message with convention header names. See the following example to find out how that works for you.</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;send with=&quot;httpResponseSender&quot;&gt;
      &lt;message&gt;
          &lt;data&gt;
              &lt;![CDATA[
                  &lt;testResponseMessage&gt;
                      &lt;text&gt;Hello Citrus Client&lt;/text&gt;
                  &lt;/testResponseMessage&gt;
              ]]&gt;
          &lt;/data&gt;
      &lt;/message&gt;
      &lt;header&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;CustomHeaderId&quot; value=&quot;${custom_header_id}&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;Content-Type&quot; value=&quot;text/xml&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;citrus_http_status_code&quot; value=&quot;200&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;citrus_http_reason_phrase&quot; value=&quot;OK&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;/header&gt;
  &lt;/send&gt;</programlisting>
        
        <para>Once more we set the custom header entry (<emphasis>CustomHeaderId</emphasis>) and a Http reserved header (<emphasis>Content-Type</emphasis>) for the response message. On top of this we are able to set the response status for
        the Http response. We use the reserved header names <emphasis>citrus_http_status_code</emphasis> in order to mark the success of the server operation. With this mechanism we can easily simulate different server behaviour such as Http 
        error response codes (e.g. 404 - Not found, 500 - Internal error). Let us have a closer look at the generated response message:</para>
        
        <programlisting>HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: text/xml;charset=UTF-8
Accept-Charset: big5, big5-hkscs, euc-jp, euc-kr, gb18030, gb2312, gbk, ibm-thai, ibm00858, ibm01140, ibm01141, ibm01142, ibm01143, ibm01144, ibm01145, ibm01146, ibm01147, ibm01148, ibm01149, ibm037, ibm1026, ibm1047, ibm273, ibm277, ibm278, ibm280, ibm284, ibm285, ibm297, ibm420, ibm424, ibm437, ibm500, ibm775, ibm850, ibm852, ibm855, ibm857, ibm860, ibm861, ibm862, ibm863, ibm864, ibm865, ibm866, ibm868, ibm869, ibm870, ibm871, ibm918, iso-2022-cn, iso-2022-jp, iso-2022-jp-2, iso-2022-kr, iso-8859-1, iso-8859-13, iso-8859-15, iso-8859-2, iso-8859-3, iso-8859-4, iso-8859-5, iso-8859-6, iso-8859-7, iso-8859-8, iso-8859-9, jis_x0201, jis_x0212-1990, koi8-r, koi8-u, macroman, shift_jis, tis-620, us-ascii, utf-16, utf-16be, utf-16le, utf-32, utf-32be, utf-32le, utf-8, windows-1250, windows-1251, windows-1252, windows-1253, windows-1254, windows-1255, windows-1256, windows-1257, windows-1258, windows-31j, x-big5-solaris, x-euc-jp-linux, x-euc-tw, x-eucjp-open, x-ibm1006, x-ibm1025, x-ibm1046, x-ibm1097, x-ibm1098, x-ibm1112, x-ibm1122, x-ibm1123, x-ibm1124, x-ibm1381, x-ibm1383, x-ibm33722, x-ibm737, x-ibm833, x-ibm834, x-ibm856, x-ibm874, x-ibm875, x-ibm921, x-ibm922, x-ibm930, x-ibm933, x-ibm935, x-ibm937, x-ibm939, x-ibm942, x-ibm942c, x-ibm943, x-ibm943c, x-ibm948, x-ibm949, x-ibm949c, x-ibm950, x-ibm964, x-ibm970, x-iscii91, x-iso-2022-cn-cns, x-iso-2022-cn-gb, x-iso-8859-11, x-jis0208, x-jisautodetect, x-johab, x-macarabic, x-maccentraleurope, x-maccroatian, x-maccyrillic, x-macdingbat, x-macgreek, x-machebrew, x-maciceland, x-macromania, x-macsymbol, x-macthai, x-macturkish, x-macukraine, x-ms932_0213, x-ms950-hkscs, x-mswin-936, x-pck, x-sjis_0213, x-utf-16le-bom, x-utf-32be-bom, x-utf-32le-bom, x-windows-50220, x-windows-50221, x-windows-874, x-windows-949, x-windows-950, x-windows-iso2022jp
Content-Length: 205
Server: Jetty(7.0.0.pre5)
  &lt;testResponseMessage&gt;
      &lt;text&gt;Hello Citrus Client&lt;/text&gt;
  &lt;/testResponseMessage&gt;</programlisting>
        
        <tip><para>You do not have to set the reason phrase all the time. It is sufficient to only set the Http status code. Citrus will automatically add the proper reason phrase for well known Http status codes.</para></tip>
        
        <para>The only thing that is missing right now is the validation of Http status codes when receiving the server response in a Citrus test case. It is very easy as you can use the Citrus reserved header names for validation, too.</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;receive with=&quot;httpResponseReceiver&quot;&gt;
      &lt;message&gt;
          &lt;data&gt;
              &lt;![CDATA[
                  &lt;testResponseMessage&gt;
                      &lt;text&gt;Hello Test Framework&lt;/text&gt;
                  &lt;/testResponseMessage&gt;
              ]]&gt;
          &lt;/data&gt;
      &lt;/message&gt;
      &lt;header&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;CustomHeaderId&quot; value=&quot;${custom_header_id}&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;citrus_http_status_code&quot; value=&quot;200&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;citrus_http_version&quot; value=&quot;HTTP/1.1&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;element name=&quot;citrus_http_reason_phrase&quot; value=&quot;OK&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;/header&gt;
  &lt;/receive&gt;</programlisting>
        
        <para>This completes the Http header processing within Citrus. On both client and server side Citrus is able to set and validate Http specific header entries which is essential for simulating Http communication.</para>        
    </section>
</chapter>