<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="templates">
    <title>Templates</title>

    <para>Templates group action sequences to a logical unit. You can think of templates as reusable components
    that are used in several tests. The maintenance is much more effective because the templates are referenced
    several times.</para>
    
    <para>The template always has a unique name. Inside a test case we call the template by this unique name. 
    Have a look at a first example:</para>
  
    <programlisting>&lt;template name=&quot;doCreateVariables&quot;&gt;
    &lt;create-variables&gt;
        &lt;variable name=&quot;var&quot; value=&quot;123456789&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/create-variables&gt;
    
    &lt;call-template name=&quot;doTraceVariables&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/template&gt;

&lt;template name=&quot;doTraceVariables&quot;&gt;
    &lt;echo&gt;
        &lt;message&gt;Current time is: ${time}&lt;/message&gt;
    &lt;/echo&gt;
    
    &lt;trace-variables/&gt;
&lt;/template&gt;</programlisting>
  
    <para>The code example above describes two template definitions. Templates hold a sequence of test 
    actions or call other templates themselves as seen in the example above.</para>
    
    <note>
      <para>The &lt;call-template&gt; action calls other templates by their name. The called
      template not necessarily has to be located in the same test case XML file. The template might be defined in
      a separate XML file other than the test case itself:</para>
    </note>
    
    <para><emphasis>XML DSL</emphasis></para>
    <programlisting>&lt;testcase name=&quot;templateTest&quot;&gt;
    &lt;variables&gt;
        &lt;variable name=&quot;myTime&quot; value=&quot;citrus:currentDate()&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/variables&gt;
    &lt;actions&gt;
        &lt;call-template name=&quot;doCreateVariables&quot;/&gt;
        
        &lt;call-template name=&quot;doTraceVariables&quot;&gt;
            &lt;parameter name=&quot;time&quot; value=&quot;${myTime}&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/call-template&gt;
    &lt;/actions&gt;
&lt;/testcase&gt;</programlisting>

    <para><emphasis>Java DSL designer</emphasis></para>
    <programlisting language="java">@CitrusTest
public void templateTest() {
    variable("myTime", "citrus:currentDate()");
    
    applyTemplate("doCreateVariables");
    
    applyTemplate("doTraceVariables")
        .parameter("time", "${myTime}");
}</programlisting>

    <para><emphasis>Java DSL runner</emphasis></para>
    <programlisting language="java">@CitrusTest
public void templateTest() {
    variable("myTime", "citrus:currentDate()");

    applyTemplate(template -> template.name("doCreateVariables"));

    applyTemplate(template -> template.name("doTraceVariables")
                    .parameter("time", "${myTime}"));
}</programlisting>
    
    <para>There is an open question when dealing with templates that are defined somewhere else outside the test case.
    How to handle variables? A templates may use different variable names then the test and vice versa. No doubt the 
    template will fail as soon as special variables with respective values are not present. Unknown variables 
    cause the template and the whole test to fail with errors.</para>
    
    <para>So a first approach would be to harmonize variable usage across templates and test cases, so that templates
    and test cases do use the same variable naming. But this approach might lead to high calibration effort. Therefore 
    templates support parameters to solve this problem. When a template is called the calling actor is able to set some 
    parameters. Let us discuss an example for this issue.</para>
    
    <para>The template &quot;doDateCoversion&quot; in the next sample uses the variable ${date}. The calling test case 
    can set this variable as a parameter without actually declaring the variable in the test itself:</para>
    
    <programlisting>&lt;call-template name=&quot;doDateCoversion&quot;&gt;
    &lt;parameter name=&quot;date&quot; value=&quot;${sampleDate}&quot;&gt;
&lt;/call-template&gt;</programlisting>
    
    <para>The variable <emphasis>sampleDate</emphasis> is already present in the test case and gets translated into the 
    <emphasis>date</emphasis> parameter. Following from that the template works fine although test and template do work on 
    different variable namings.</para>
    
    <para>With template parameters you are able to solve the calibration effort when working with templates and variables. 
    It is always a good idea to check the used variables/parameters inside a template when calling it. There might be a 
    variable that is not declared yet inside your test. So you need to define this value as a parameter.</para>
    
    <para>Template parameters may contain more complex values like XML fragments. The call-template action offers following 
    CDATA variation for defining complex parameter values:</para>
    
    <programlisting>&lt;call-template name=&quot;printXMLPayload&quot;&gt;
    &lt;parameter name=&quot;payload&quot;&gt;
      &lt;value&gt;
        &lt;![CDATA[
          &lt;HelloRequest xmlns=&quot;http://www.consol.de/schemas/samples/sayHello.xsd&quot;&gt;
            &lt;Text&gt;Hello South ${var}&lt;/Text&gt;
          &lt;/HelloRequest&gt;
        ]]&gt;
      &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;/parameter&gt;
&lt;/call-template&gt;</programlisting>
    
    <important>
        <para>When a template works on variable values and parameters changes to these variables will automatically affect the variables 
        in the whole test. So if you change a variable's value inside a template and the variable is defined inside the test case the
        changes will affect the variable in a global context. We have to be careful with this when executing a template several
        times in a test, especially in combination with parallel containers (see <xref linkend="containers-parallel"/>).</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;parallel&gt;
    &lt;call-template name=&quot;print&quot;&gt;
        &lt;parameter name=&quot;param1&quot; value=&quot;1&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;parameter name=&quot;param2&quot; value=&quot;Hello Europe&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/call-template&gt;
    &lt;call-template name=&quot;print&quot;&gt;
        &lt;parameter name=&quot;param1&quot; value=&quot;2&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;parameter name=&quot;param2&quot; value=&quot;Hello Asia&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/call-template&gt;
    &lt;call-template name=&quot;print&quot;&gt;
        &lt;parameter name=&quot;param1&quot; value=&quot;3&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;parameter name=&quot;param2&quot; value=&quot;Hello Africa&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/call-template&gt;
&lt;/parallel&gt;</programlisting>
        
        <para>In the listing above a template <emphasis>print</emphasis> is called several times in a parallel container. The parameter values
        will be handled in a global context, so it is quite likely to happen that the template instances influence each other during execution.
        We might get such print messages:</para>
        
        <programlisting>2. Hello Europe
2. Hello Africa
3. Hello Africa</programlisting>
        
        <para>Index parameters do not fit and the message <emphasis>'Hello Asia'</emphasis> is completely gone. This is because templates 
        overwrite parameters to each other as they are executed in parallel at the same time. To avoid this behavior we need to tell the template 
        that it should handle parameters as well as variables in a local context. This will enforce that each template instance is working on a 
        dedicated local context. See the <emphasis>global-context</emphasis> attribute that is set to <emphasis>false</emphasis> in this example:</para>
        
        <programlisting>&lt;template name=&quot;print&quot; global-context=&quot;false&quot;&gt;
    &lt;echo&gt;
        &lt;message&gt;${param1}.${param2}&lt;/message&gt;
    &lt;/echo&gt;
&lt;/template&gt;</programlisting>
        
        <para>After that template instances won't influence each other anymore. But notice that variable changes inside the template then do not affect 
        the test case neither.</para>
    </important>
</chapter>