<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="whatsnew">
  <title>What's new?!</title>

  <para>The new Citrus release introduces new features and changes that we discuss in the following sections. We want you to get an overview of what has happened in the last release so you can
  identify the new stuff which is of interest for you.</para>
  
  <section id="whatsnew-actors">
    <title>Test actors</title>

    <para>We introduced a new concept of test actors for sending and receiving test actions. This enables you to link a test actor (e.g. interface partner application, backend application) to a test
    action in your test. Following from that you can enable/disable test actors and all linked test actions very easy. This enables us to reuse Citrus test cases in end-to-end test scenarios where
    not all interface partners get simulated by Citrus. If you like to read more about this concept follow the detailed instruction in <xref linkend="test-actors"/>.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="whatsnew-soap-http-errors">
    <title>Simulate Http error codes with SOAP</title>

    <para>In case Citrus provides SOAP WebServices as a server we can now simulate Http error codes like 404 Not found and 500 Internal server error. This was not possible before so the SOAP server always responsed
    with a proper SOAP response or SOAP fault. See <xref linkend="soap-http-errors"/> for details.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="whatsnew-actions">
    <title>New test actions</title>
    
    <para>We introduced some completely new test actions:</para> 
    
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>AntRunAction</emphasis> This action executes one or more ANT build targets on a build.xml file. You can specify build properties that get passed to the ANT build and you can add a 
        custom build listener. In case the ANT build run fails the test fails accordingly with the build exception. See <xref linkend="actions-antrun"/> for details.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>See also our test action section (<xref linkend="actions"/>) for detailed instructions how to use the new test actions.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="whatsnew-functions">
    <title>New functions</title>
    
    <para>Citrus provides several default functions that will ease the testers life. We continuously :</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Nothing yet!</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>See <xref linkend="functions"/> for detail descriptions of each function.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="whatsnew-bugfixes">
    <title>Bugfixes</title>
    
    <para>Bug fixing is part of our daily business. Finding and solving issues makes Citrus better every day. For a detailed
    bugfix listing please refer to the complete changes log.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="whatsnew-upgrading">
    <title>Upgrading from version 1.2</title>
    
    <para>If you are coming from Citrus 1.2 final you may have to look at the following points in order to have a smooth upgrade to the latest release version.</para>
    
    <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Nothing yet</emphasis> Nothing to do yet!</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>