<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Copyright 2006-2016 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<chapter id="zookeeper">
  <title>Zookeeper support</title>

  <para>Citrus provides configuration components and test actions for interaction with Zookeeper. The Citrus zookeeper
    client component executes Zookeeper commands for interacting with Zookeeper to do things like creating a new node,
    checking to see if node exists, deleting a node or getting and setting node data. As a user you can execute
    Zookeeper commands as part of a Citrus test and validate possible command results.
  </para>

  <para>Before you can interact with a zookeeper server you have to configure the zookeeper client. A sample
    configuration is provided below describing the configuration options available:
    TODO MM
  </para>

  <para>After configuring the zookeeper client connecting to the sever is a piece of cake. Samples of all the
    operations using both the java and the xml DSL are provided below.
    TODO MM
  </para>

  <para>
    info: Retrieves the cuttent state of the client connection
    create: Creates a znode in a specified path of the ZooKeeper namespace
    delete: Deletes a znode from a specified path of the ZooKeeper namespace
    exists: Checks if a znode exists in the path
    getChildren: Gets a list of children of a znode
    getData: Gets the data associated with a znode
    setData: Sets/writes data into the data field of a znode
    TODO MM
  </para>

</chapter>