<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section id="actions-java">
    <title>Java</title>

    <para>The test framework offers a service action to instantiate any Java class and run any method through Java
    reflection. Using this you can invoke any Java based mechanism like command CLI’s or other Java
    applications.</para>
    
    <programlisting>
    &lt;java class=&quot;de.consol.testsuite.util.InvocationDummy&quot;&gt;
        &lt;constructor&gt;
            &lt;argument type=&quot;&quot;&gt;Test Invocation&lt;/argument&gt;
        &lt;/constructor&gt;
        &lt;method name=&quot;invoke&quot;&gt;
            &lt;argument type=&quot;String[]&quot;&gt;1,2&lt;/argument&gt;
        &lt;/method&gt;
    &lt;/java&gt;
    
    &lt;java class=&quot;de.consol.testsuite.util.InvocationDummy&quot;&gt;
        &lt;constructor&gt;
            &lt;argument type=&quot;&quot;&gt;Test Invocation&lt;/argument&gt;
        &lt;/constructor&gt;
        &lt;method name=&quot;invoke&quot;&gt;
            &lt;argument type=&quot;int&quot;&gt;4&lt;/argument&gt;
            &lt;argument type=&quot;String&quot;&gt;Test Invocation&lt;/argument&gt;
            &lt;argument type=&quot;boolean&quot;&gt;true&lt;/argument&gt;
        &lt;/method&gt;
    &lt;/java&gt;
    
    &lt;java class=&quot;de.consol.testsuite.util.InvocationDummy&quot;&gt;
        &lt;method name=&quot;main&quot;&gt;
            &lt;argument type=&quot;String[]&quot;&gt;4,Test,true &lt;/argument&gt;
        &lt;/method&gt;
    &lt;/java&gt;
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>The Java class that will be called is specified by fully qualified class name in the class attribute.
    Constructor arguments can be added through the &lt;constructor&gt; element. Every &lt;argument&gt; declares a
    constructor argument. The type of the argument can be defined with the respective attribute &quot;type&quot;. The
    default type would be String.</para>
    
    <para>The method is simply specified by its name. Arguments can be added through the element &lt;argument&gt;
    as shown in the second example.</para>
    
    <para>As you can see several data types are supported. To specify string arrays as arguments, useful when
    calling main methods, you should take a look at the third example given. Here you can see that colon
    separated strings are automatically converted to string arrays.</para>
    
    <para>Simple data types are defined by their name (int, boolean, float etc.). Be sure that the invoked method
    and class constructor fit your arguments and vice versa. Otherwise Java will throw errors because the
    arguments do not fit the Java code.</para>
</section>