<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="cleanup">
    <title>Test case cleanup</title>

    <para>This section deals with a special section inside the test case that is executed even in case errors
    did occur during the test. Lets say you have started a Jetty web server instance at the beginning of the 
    test case and you need to shutdown the server when the test has finished its work. Or as a second example
    imagine that you have prepared some data inside the database at the beginning of your test and 
    you want to make sure that the data is cleaned up at the end of the test case.</para>
    
    <para>In both situations we might run into some problems when the test failed. 
    We face the problem that the whole test case will terminate immediately in case of errors. Cleanup tasks 
    at the end of the test action chain may not be executed correctly.</para>
    
    <para>Dirty states inside the database or still running server instances then might cause problems for 
    upcoming test cases. To avoid this problems you should use the cleanup block of the test case. The &lt;cleanup&gt; 
    section contains actions that are executed even in case the test fails. Using this strategy the database 
    cleaning tasks mentioned before will find execution in every case (success or failure).</para>
    
    <para>The following example shows how to use the cleanup section at the end of a test:</para>
  
    <programlisting>
  &lt;testcase name=&quot;cleanupTest&quot;&gt;
      &lt;variables&gt;
          &lt;variable name=&quot;orderId&quot; value=&quot;1&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;variable name=&quot;date&quot; 
                       value=&quot;citrus:currentDate('dd.MM.yyyy')&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;/variables&gt;
      &lt;actions&gt;
          &lt;updateDatabase connect=&quot;databaseAccess&quot;&gt;
              &lt;statement&gt;
                  INSERT INTO ORDERS VALUES (${orderId}, 1, 1, '${date}')
              &lt;/statement&gt;
          &lt;/updateDatabase&gt;
          
          &lt;echo&gt;
              &lt;message&gt;
                  ORDER creation time: ${date}
              &lt;/message&gt;
          &lt;/echo&gt;
      &lt;/actions&gt;
      &lt;cleanup&gt;
          &lt;updateDatabase connect=&quot;databaseAccess&quot;&gt;
              &lt;statement&gt;DELETE FROM ORDERS WHERE ORDER_ID='${orderId}'&lt;/statement&gt;
          &lt;/updateDatabase&gt;
      &lt;/cleanup&gt;
  &lt;/testcase&gt;
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>In the example the first action creates an entry in the database using an <literal>INSERT</literal> statement. 
    To be sure that the entry in the database is deleted after the test, the cleanup section contains the respective 
    <literal>DELETE</literal> statement that is always executed regardless the test case state (successful or failed).</para>
    
</chapter>