<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <para>Integration testing can be very hard, especially when there is no sufficient tool support. Unit testing 
  is flavored with fantastic tools and APIs like JUnit, TestNG, and EasyMock which support you in writing automated tests. 
  A tester who is in charge of integration testing may lack of tool support for automated integration testing.
   
  In a typical Service-oriented Architecture (SOA) with enterprise applications the test team has to deal with different
  interfaces and various transport protocols. Without sufficient tool support the automated integration testing of message-based 
  interactions between interface partners is exhausting and sometimes barely possible.</para> 
  
  <para>The tester is forced to simulate several interface partners trying to simulate a chain of actions and messages. Simulating
  the behavior of interface partners in a automated test causes severe problems regarding maintainability and interoperability. 
  It is not unusual that a tester simulates external applications manually during the test, because of lacking tool support. The 
  manual test approach is very time consuming and error prone, because the process is not repeatable and the tester manually validates 
  the success.</para>
  
  <para>The Citrus framework gives a complete test automation tool for integration testing of enterprise applications in a 
  Service.oriented Architecture. Every time a change was made in the application all automated Citrus tests ensure the stability of 
  interfaces and message communication. Regression testing and continuous integration testing is very easy. Citrus is designed to
  provide fully automated integration testing of whole end-to-end use cases with effective simulation of interface partners across
  various messaging transports and automated validation and functionality checks.</para>
  
  <para>This documentation provides a reference guide to all features of the Citrus test framework. It gives a detailed picture 
  of effective integration testing with automated integration test environments. Since this document is considered to be under 
  construction, please do not hesitate to give any comments or requests to us using our user or support mailing lists.</para>
  
</preface>